Contact

www.linkedin.com/in/mjpakdel (LinkedIn)

Top Skills

Statistics

Research

Economics

Languages

Persian (Native or Bilingual) English (Full Professional)

Certifications

AWS Certified Developer - Associate

Machine Learning Foundations: A Case Study Approach

Databricks Certified Developer - Apache Spark 2.x for Python

Machine Learning: Regression, Classification, Clustering and Retrieval, Recommender Systems and Dimensionality Reduction

exam P, FM, and MFE

MJ Pakdel, PhD

Lead Data Scientist at Nielsen

Orange County, California Area

Summary

Blends academic training in statistics, economics, and finance with hands-on experience in machine learning, data engineering, automation, and big data to offer employers a track record of delivering tasks accurately, efficiently, and quickly. Collaborative team player with strong quantitative, decision making, multitasking, and communication skills.

Experience

Nielsen Senior Data Scientist June 2015 - Present (4 years 10 months) Irvine/CA

- 1- Developing machine learning techniques to build models that address business needs.
- 2- Utilizing tools such as Python, Tableau, SQL, SAS, Spark, etc. to perform complex data analysis
- 3- Creating data visualizations to provide management insight into complex business problems in Tableau and Spotfire
- 4- Interacting with the client to provide an explanation of products in a format that meets their level of understanding

Select Machine Learning Project: The business goal was to replace a variable which was collected nationally using annual survey with a different variable. The new variable was intended to be driven at no cost using Nielsen's panel data. I developed a new variable (called acculturation variable) using advanced machine learning algorithms (decision trees), which was a perfect substitute for the traditionally used variable in terms of predicting power. After retiring the old survey process, millions of dollars were saved for the company.

Select Automation Project: The business goal was to automate the stormy report which was delivered 3 times a week. A team of 5 persons in India had to input over 30 parameters, run several Fortran, SAS, and Unix shell scripts,

supervise the process, finalize, and deliver the report. The team that I built and led as the main developer, replaced the legacy process with a Python software that shrank the human role to zero at execution, data retrieval, and report creation stages. Also, The turnaround time of report reduced from 2 hours to under 1 minute.

Select Big Data Project: My team designed a self-modifying python software to retrieve several billion records in HDFS format from Amazon S3 buckets. The big data was then processed using computationally intensive algorithms. Several big data optimization techniques were implemented to make the process in Spark feasible. The delivered software surpassed leadership's expectations in terms of computational budget and turnaround time.

Northern Illinois University Economics Instructor January 2015 - May 2015 (5 months)

- •Organizing and presenting instructional material at scheduled times and places in accordance with the university catalog descriptions, course syllabi and outlines, and class schedules.
- •Improving communication skills by working with a group of 50 students, learning presentation skills necessary to present the course materials during the class.
- •Maintaining discipline and order during instructional activities

IHS

Contract Analyst March 2014 - June 2014 (4 months)

- Monitoring of open-source intelligence inputs, such as local media and social media, to collect risk relevant indicator events for Iran.
- Reporting accurately, objectively and concisely against political or economic risk increasing or decreasing in Iran to IHS OSINT database.

System Analysts Company
Research Analyst
October 2008 - June 2009 (9 months)

• Investigating the criteria of Credit Rating of customers for Omid Investment Bank, involvement in literature reviews, preparation of presentations and final reports.

- Preparing a manual for assessing credit risk of mortgage loans' applicants for the Parsian Bank of Iran. The project received bank's Project of the Year Award due to its comprehensive and accurate analysis.
- Investigating the Methods of Risk Management for Iran Khodro Company, Involvement in literature reviews, case study and benchmarking.

Boorsiran security trading company (Headquarter in Iran) Risk Analytics expert February 2007 - February 2009 (2 years 1 month)

Tehran, Iran

- Designing customized investment solutions for the clients based on the type of risk aversion.
- Analyzing the market risk factors that may affect the share price of the company's portfolio. Big market data was stored and handled in SQL server.
 The market risk of portfolio decreased 30% by hedging the portfolio against these risk factors while ensuring the enhancements of portfolio's price.
- Preparing the weekly reports about the latest changes in the domestic and global financial markets for the CEO.

Education

Northern Illinois University
Doctor of Philosophy (Ph.D.), Economics · (2010 - 2016)

Northern Illinois University

Master's Degree, Statistics · (2013 - 2015)

Shahid Beheshti University

Master of Science (M.S.), Finance, General · (2007 - 2010)